<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Brief and true account of the sufferings of the Church of Scotland occasioned by the Episcopalians since the year 1660 being a vindication of Their Majesties government in that kingdom, relating to the proceedings against the bishops and clergy there : with some animadversions upon a libel intituled, The present state and condition of the clergy and Church of Scotland.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29422</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4533</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8736</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11983228</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11983228</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51902</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29422)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51902)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 56:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Brief and true account of the sufferings of the Church of Scotland occasioned by the Episcopalians since the year 1660 being a vindication of Their Majesties government in that kingdom, relating to the proceedings against the bishops and clergy there : with some animadversions upon a libel intituled, The present state and condition of the clergy and Church of Scotland.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland.</term>
               <term>Episcopal Church in Scotland --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51902:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51902:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Brief and True Account OF THE SUFFERINGS OF THE <hi>Church of Scotland,</hi> Occaſioned by the Epiſcopalians Since the Year 1660.</p>
            <p>Being a Vindication of their Majeſties Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in that Kingdom, relating to the Proceedings againſt the Biſhops and Clergy there.</p>
            <p>With ſome Animadverſions upon a Libel In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>The preſent State and Condition of the Clergy and Church of</hi> Scotland.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:51902:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51902:2"/>
            <head>A Brief and True Account of the Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſince the Year <hi>1660, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SEEING it has always been juſtly called intolerable Arrogance in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to uſurp the Epithet of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> when the far greater Number of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans decline her Communion; It may very well be called a Superlative Impudence in the late Prelats of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and their Clergy, to arrogate as theirs the Name of that Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Church, when by the <hi>Convention</hi> they were voted, <hi>the great and inſupportable Grievance of the Nation.</hi> By their Majeſties and Parliament, the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> hath been demoliſhed, as contrary to the Inclinations of the Generality of the People. And by the Laws of God the Majority of their Adherents are uncapable of the diſtinguiſhing Priviledges of Church-Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, becauſe of their vicious Lives.</p>
            <p>Which leads me to conſider, how unbecoming it is for them to reflect upon the Nation as ſupine and indevote; <hi>Quis tule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Gracchos de ſeditione querentes.</hi> If it were not known, that it's ordinary for the greateſt Whore to call Whore firſt, one would take them to be very devout Men who thus exclaim againſt Indevotion: but O Helliſh Diſſimulation and Malice! herein they imitate the Devil himſelf, who firſt tempts, and then accuſes; tho' 'tis too viſible that their Conſciences are paſt feeling, being ſeared as with a hot Iron. There are Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in the Nation who remember, That when their Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy was reſtored there, the Devil, who ſeemed to be bound for ſome time before, was let looſe, the Floodgates of all Impiety and Wickedneſs were ſet open, and Hell did triumph in its Conqueſts over that Nation, and diſplayed its Banner not only againſt Religion, but even Morality: which the Prelates and their Adherents were ſo far from oppoſing, that they indulged
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51902:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he People, but eſpecially, the Gentry, in their Wickedneſs, as knowing That to be the only Method to ſecure them on their Side; inſomuch, that Curſing, Swearing, Drunkenneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> became as infallible Characteriſticks to diſtinguiſh a <hi>Prelatiſt</hi> from a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> as <hi>Shibboleth</hi> was to diſcern the <hi>Gileadites</hi> from thoſe of <hi>Ephraim:</hi> which the following Inſtances, amongſt the many hundred more that might be given, do ſufficiently evince.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>booted Apoſtles,</hi> as Dragoons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to convert the Nation, (wherein once at leaſt we were in faſhion before <hi>France,</hi>) ſometimes they apprehended Perſons by Miſtake, but as ſoon as they heard them pronounce the <hi>Shibbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth</hi> of Curſing and Swearing, they were preſently ſet at liberty, with the Character of an Honeſt-man, and <hi>no Whigg;</hi> the name then for the Presbyterians of that Nation.</p>
            <p>And in the Weſt of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where ſo great a Reformation was wrought, that in ſeveral Pariſhes there was not the leaſt minced Oath to be heard; when thoſe Miſcreants were ſent amongſt them, to force a Compliance with the Prelatical Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, thruſt upon them as Miniſters, without their conſents; the poor Children hearing their execrable Oaths, and not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they meant; (having never heard ſuch before) ask'd their-Parents in the greateſt ſimplicity imaginable, the meaning of ſuch and ſuch Words: a hopeful Church, that uſes ſuch as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers; but it's too well known there that ſuch kind of Men were the greateſt Abettors of Them, and their Cauſe. And on the other hand, when ever it could be ſaid of a Man, <hi>Behold, he Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;</hi> it might be ſaid with equal certainty, Behold, he loatheth the Curates and their Miniſtry; excepting a very few <hi>Presbyterians</hi> who always held it lawful to hear them, but never could own that they were the Inſtruments of their Converſion. Yea, the Miſcreants themſelves were ſo ſenſible of it, that aſſoon as ever any of their Pariſhioners begun to ſet their face Heavenward, and worſhip God in, and with their Families, they were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently the Objects of their Hatred and Perſecution. One re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Inſtance, amongſt thouſands, there was in <hi>Eaſt-Lothian:</hi> A conſiderable Yeoman, called <hi>Sherrift,</hi> or <hi>Sherwood,</hi> having a Son, who by hearing ſome of the Presbyterian Miniſters, was convinced of his ſinful State by Nature, and the neceſſity of a Saviour; and accordingly, retired Morning and Evening to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51902:3"/>bewail, himſelf and ſeek God. His Father was ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmed at it, that his Son ſhould turn <hi>Whig,</hi> and <hi>howl</hi> and <hi>whine</hi> by himſelf, (as mourning for Sin, and ſeeking of God by Secret Prayer, was then called in the Epiſcopal Dialect) that he complained of it to his Pariſh Prieſt, lamenting that he had loſt one of the hopefulleſt young Men in <hi>Lothain.</hi>—The God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Miſcreant, that he might diſcover himſelf to be of the true <hi>Egyptian</hi> Brood, who reflected upon the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> as idle, when they ſought leave to ſerve God, adviſed the Father to raiſe his Son betimes in a Morning, and work him hard all Day, and he would undertake he ſhould forget to ſay his Prayers er'e he went to bed at night. Adding further, That to convince him what kind of villanous Preachers they were whom his Son heard, and ſee the wicked Practices of theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticlers (whom the Prelatiſts charged with uncleanneſs then, as their Predeceſſors the Pagans did the Primitive Chriſtians of old) he would lend him his Horſe to ride to a Conventicle. Hereupon the Father took an opportunity to follow his Son to a Meeting, where it pleaſed God to touch his Heart by the Word preached, ſo that he found himſelf under a Neceſſity of practiſing what he had formerly condemned in his Son; and a little while after they were both of them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to Sufferings for Nonconformity.</p>
            <p>And that the World may have a further taſte of the Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and of their way of Converting, I ſhall give you another very remarkable Inſtance, which may ſufficiently diſcover what their Deſign was to convert the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to, if we conſider the Means and Inſtruments made uſe of in ſo good a Work.</p>
            <p>When the Magiſtrates exacting the Mulcts enacted by Law upon ſuch as abſented from hearing the Curates, did not prevail upon the Weſtern People to own thoſe as their Miniſters who were not ordained according to the Word, and intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon people by Violence; They ſent Souldiers upon free Quarter to drive or drag them to Church, who uſually ſtaid till they had conſumed the ſubſtance of their Landlords; and many times would force them to drive their own Cattle to Market, and ſell them at an under-rate, and then rob them of the Money: and, moreover, behaved themſelves in ſo beaſtial a manner, that no Marriageable-Woman could with ſafety ſtay
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51902:4"/>at home, by which (the Men being alſofled for Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity) it came to paſs that many poor Infants were left in the Houſe, as not able to endure the fatigue of travelling, and lying by night in the cold Mountains, who were ſo barbarouſly uſed by the prelatical Apoſtles, that they could not ſatisfy their hunger with the brother wherein their Parents Cattle had been boiled, till the Souldiers Dogs had firſt lapped and left it.—And their uſual ſaying was, We came to deſtroy, and we will deſtroy, and all this before the People could be charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with any Inſurrection, but meerly upon the Account of not hearing.—And to teſtify what reſpect thoſe infernal Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries had for Religion, inſtead of going to Church themſelves, whither they were ſent to drive others, a Party of them aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled at a Mercat-Croſs, and one of their Number read ſome verſes of an old amorous Scotiſh Poem, called <hi>the Cherry and the Sloe,</hi> inſtead of a Sermon, and they ſung another part of it inſtead of a Pſalm, without any Animadverſion from their devote Church or Pious State for ſuch tremendous Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm.—And to conſummate the Miſery of the poor People, Sir <hi>Ja. Turner,</hi> the Commander in chief of thoſe helliſh E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Miſſionaries, being conſcious that he had exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the bounds of his Ungodly Commiſſion, extorted a Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate from the diſtreſſed Country, that he had behaved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf according to Law: which horrible Oppreſſion, together with their Barbarous Uſage of ſome honeſt Men (againſt whom they had nothing but the Matters of their God) whom they tied Neck and heels together, and caſt two of them, one to ballance another, on Horſe-back, (as Butchers do Sheep de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for the Slaughter) occaſioned a ſmall Number to take Arms in 1666 (becauſe they could not otherwiſe be ſafe from the inſults of the Souldiers and Prelatiſts) that they might preſent a Petition to the Council for Redreſs of thoſe Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances.—The Prelatical Party having got it made Treaſon to Petition the King otherwiſe than by his Counſel, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compoſed of the wicked Biſhops, and their debauched Adherents, they would be ſure to ſtifle all Remonſtrances a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Barbarity, that they ſhould not ſee Light.</p>
            <p>But to return to our Author: He tells us, <hi>That the Scots Epiſcopal Clergy pray heartily that the Diſcipline, Order, and Conſtitution of the Engliſh Church might be ſettled amongſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51902:4"/>them, to prevent Supineneſs and Indevotgion</hi>—which is a Maſs of Ignorance and Nonſenſe. Have they not had the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Diſcipline almoſt theſe thirty Years? and is not that the diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England?</hi>—How come they then to pray ſo heartily to have that which they enjoyed?—Had not the King the naming, or, if you will, the making of the Biſhops, they and the Patrons the making of the Prieſts, and Laws to compel the People to own them as ſuch? And was not that the Conſtitution of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Then what needed they deſire that which they had? And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of all this, Is not that Supineneſs and Indevotion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their own hearers? I appeal to their Conſciences if it be not: Then how doth it appear that the Diſcipline of the Engliſh Church is ſo excellent a Mean to prevent it?—But you'l ſay, they wanted the Common-Prayer and Ceremonies. —True, but that's neither the Conſtitution nor Diſcipline, but the Worſhip of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> and whether that be ſo excellent a Mean to prevent Supineneſs and Indevotion, any Man may judg who will but caſt his Eyes about him, and ſee whether Supineneſs and Indevotion, and their Conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitants, Swearing, Drinking, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be more the Character of thoſe of that Church, or of Diſſenters from it.—I am ſure they who obſerved the Practice of the D. of <hi>York</hi>'s Family, where that worſhip was zealouſly maintained when he was in <hi>Scotland,</hi> had no Reaſon to admire the Effects of that Devotion, for they and their Maſter together turn'd the Palace into a Baudy-houſe, and indeavoured to make the whole City a Stews; wherein that Epiſcopal Concurrence to ſo good a Work might not be wanting, the Biſhop of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> lent a helping-hand, and was taken in the very Act of filthineſs with one of his Ladies of Honour, by a Lady of greateſt Quality in that Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and this very Biſhop was the moſt zealous of any for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy and Ceremonies, and I underſtand ſince one of thoſe who our Pamphleteer ſays, refreſh'd their Souls with that kind of Worſhip now in their Diſtreſs. But if they had conſulted their own Honour, they would never have brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of ſuch a Proſelyte, who is fitter for a Stallion; or, if now ſuperannuated for that Work, to be a Pimp to a Baudy-houſe, than owned as a Member of any Church, and much leſs as a Right Reverend Father in God, he having been always better
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51902:5"/>at kiſſing his Band-ſtrings in the middle of his Sermon, to give Aſſurance to a Whore that he could think of her in the middle of his Devotion, than to govern in the Church.</p>
            <p>Neither do I think that the Reformedneſs of thoſe of the Church-Communion in the Borders whence our Pamphleteer pretends to write, can be any Tentation to our Epiſcopal Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, to deſire the aforeſaid Worſhip, for I my ſelf not many Years ago have ſeen Piping, Dancing, and playing amongſt ſuch on the Sabbath, where many times the Prieſt was Spectator, if not Partner: And until the <hi>Scots</hi> Presbyterian Miniſters by their Preaching, reformed that Country, ſuch Practices were very ordinary. And Malice it ſelf muſt needs own that the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of ſuch have repreſſed Theft, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> more on the Borders, than either the Laws of the State, or the Preaching and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> yea many of thoſe who were infamous Thieves, were never moleſted for that while they heard their Pariſh-Prieſts, but upon turning from theſe evil ways, have on the Account of their Nonconformity been expoſed by thoſe Hirelings to great Sufferings, who belike were of the ſame Opinion with that infamous Parricide, Sorcerer, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous Apoſtate, <hi>Sharp,</hi> Archbiſhop of St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> who having ſent for that gallant and religious Gentleman Sir <hi>Will. Douglas,</hi> late of <hi>Cavers,</hi> inſtead of civil Behaviour to a Perſon of his Honour, Deſcent, and Quality, who has better to hold his Stirrup than the chief of the Biſhop's Family, the infamous Varlot upbraided him thus,—Sir <hi>William,</hi> I underſtand you are a good Countryman, and ſuppreſs theft in the Borders, but you entertain that which is worſe at your Houſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Miniſters. To which the worthy Gentleman, with a Greatneſs of Soul ſuitable to the Grandeur of his Family, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to return any Anſwer, but immediately turn'd his back upon and left the infamous Villain to corrode his own viperous Bowels with his inhumane Fury.</p>
            <p>Yea the <hi>Scots</hi> Epiſcopalians themſelves were ſo ſenſible of the remiſs Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that when any of their Daughters had been impregnated in Fornication or Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, it was uſual amongſt ſuch as were willing to avoid the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of it, to ſend them over the Borders to be delivered, which in that Country is called the ſpinning of a blue Web: And the honeſt Prieſts for a little Spell of Money, never refuſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51902:5"/>Baptiſm to ſuch Brats; or to couple Whores and Rogues toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which are there called half-Mark-Marriages, when by their previous Dalliances the Belly begins to ſwell, ſo that for Shame they cannot in that Condition go to be married in their own Country: and I have heard it as the Encomium of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Parſon, God be with him, he never refuſed to make a Chriſtened Soul, or a married Couple. But leſt any ſhould ſay that theſe are malicious Reflections upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I anſwer, that a Poet of their own, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringil</hi> in his <hi>Ceremony-Mongers Character</hi> and other Books, ſays a great deal worſe, and in expreſs Terms, That it is the worſt conſtituted Church in the World. But that which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to confound the Impudence of Gain-ſayers; The moſt part of the Abuſes which Diſſenters accuſe the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> of are named, and a Reformation of them commanded by his Majeſty in his late gracious Letter to the Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> which as it hath heightned and confirmed the good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which all honeſt Men had of him, it hath alſo incenſed the Debauchees and high-flown Prelatiſts, who upbraid him, as now beginning to diſcover himſelf, and ſay that it were not beſt for him to meddle too much. Which verifies the Obſervation that Diſſenters have always entertained of thoſe Tantivies, that let their Hyperbolical Pretenſions of Zeal for Religion and Loyalty be what they will, if the King put but forth his Hand and touch them, they will curſe him to his Face; and rather than part with an Inch of Superſtition or a ſwiniſh Luſt, will, as the Party have always done, ſay a Confederacy with <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> as times paſt and preſent do evidence beyond Contradiction; of which, if my deſigned Brevity would permit, I could give Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Inſtances out of their own Authors, from the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to this very Day. But to conclude this Point, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to the World that the Presbyterian Diſcipline is infinitely beyond that ſo much idolized Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> let them give ſuch an Inſtance as this, of the now Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Miniſters of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> who charged their Elders, at their Election, to viſit the Pariſh two by two, and ſee that the Maſter of every Family prayed in his Family; and if he were not able to do it, that they ſhould inſtruct him, and pray with the Family themſelves. Neither is this a Novelty to capital Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planſe, but the old Practice of the Presbyterians both at home
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51902:6"/>and abroad, where the Government did not obſtruct it, and which God hath many times bleſs'd with Succeſs. Thoſe being Helps of his own Appointment to aſſiſt his faithful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in the Diſcharge of their Paſtoral Duties. And we ſhould be very glad to ſee the Church of <hi>England</hi> as conſcientiouſly diſcharge what Diſcipline their own Canons enjoyn, and his Majeſty hath now commanded, as the aforeſaid Miniſters are to put theirs in practice out of mere Principle, and without any ſuch Command: but this is more than we can hope, or their Church bear, as now conſtitute, which time will verify. —Nor do we want Teſtimony from Officers of their own Communion, of the good Diſcipline of Presbyterian Families in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where they quartered, and as a thing extraordinary to them, gave an Account by Letter to their Friends, that they were quartered in <hi>Scots</hi> Presbyterian Houſe, who read, pray'd, and ſung Pſalms in their Families twice a Day: — And yet thoſe are the Men whom the Church of <hi>England</hi> will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit into Command, though they have ſufficiently evidenced their Courage, Chriſtianity, and Loyalty in the Deſence of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> &amp;c. whereof others baſely and maliciouſly have robbed them of the Honour.</p>
            <p>What our Author means by the Orthodox Principles the <hi>Scots</hi> Univerſity were ſo careful to infuſe into their Students, or by the great and diſtinguiſhing Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> defended in Print by an eminent Profeſſor at <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> I know not: When I was at the Univerſity of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> about 9 Years ago, the <hi>Aſſemblies Confeſſion of Faith</hi> was taught there, and generally by the Epiſcopalians through the Kingdom, though their Practice and the ſame were as much oppoſite as black is to white. — And I cannot think our Author will allow that <hi>Confeſſion</hi> as Orthodox, leſt he ſhould thwart a Church-of-<hi>England</hi>-Jury who brought it in as a Libel not many Years ago; it being alſo formerly damned by the Univerſity of <hi>Oxon:</hi> And that the Church of <hi>England</hi> (though different in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Ceremonies) held any Doctrine which diſtinguiſhed her from other Reformed Churches, none ever averred, except it were that new up-ſtart ſlaviſh Doctrine of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> in the ſenſe of the preſent diſloyal Recuſant Clergy, whereof as ſhe had the Diſhonour to be the Mother, ſhe has alſo the Ignominy to be the Murderer, having baſely cut its
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51902:6"/>Throat, as Harlots uſe to do ſometimes with their ſpurious Brood, whereof if their darling K. <hi>James</hi> had had timely No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, a thouſand to one if ever the Nation had ſeen the bleſſed Day of an Abdication and Vacancy of his Throne, and the ſame filled with the beſt of Kings, as it is now, to the Terror of Papiſts and their Adherents.—But if, as there is all the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the World to believe, they are the Apoſtles of Paſſive Obedience, whoſe Cauſe this Man advocates, we know what Friend he is to the Government:— For if they believe their own Doctrine, they muſt needs look upon reſiſting and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throning the greateſt Tyrant as unlawful, and conſequently diſapprove of what the Nation has done againſt the late King, and look upon their preſent Majeſties as Uſurpers, whom they may lawfully reſiſt and depoſe when they have ſufficient Force, which that they may attain we need not doubt of their Zeal to buz about their venemous Principles, and intoxicate the Minds of thoſe, who that they may without Controul enſlave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others, by their Profanity, to the Devil (which his preſent Majeſty by his Letter aforeſaid has ſhewed himſelf an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to) they will freely render Themſelves and the Nations, Slaves to the Tyranny of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What was the Behaviour of the Epiſcopal Clergy at the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of <hi>Bothwel</hi>-Bridg, our Author ſays every one knows: but I believe if all the Truth were told, he himſelf knows lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of it, and I am confident helooks upon himſelf as ſome Body, and would be very angry if his Neighbours did not ſo too.—However, ſeeing he hath put me in Mind of it, I'le let ſome know what I am ſure he is not willing they ſhould; — which is thus, — When the extraordinary Hazard of thoſe in whoſe Houſes they met, the frequent Surprizes and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Uſage of thoſe who did meet, and the Bleſſing of God upon the Endeavours of the Preachers did ſo much increaſe the Number of Meeters, that they could not with Conveniency and Safety be accommodated with Houſes, they betook themſelves to the Field, where it pleaſed God by the Fooliſhneſs of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (or in the Epiſcopal Dialect) Fanatical Preachers to convert ſo many Souls, that the more they were oppreſſed, the more they grew; and notwithſtanding the Cannibal Laws againſt them, and the Malice of the Epiſcopalians which carried them beyond the Extent of thoſe Laws, the Churches were more
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51902:7"/>and more emptied, and Meetings more and more crowded; where a Frame ſo far from ſupineneſs or indevotion was ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fible, that the ſighs and groans of thoſe who were pricked at the Heart for Sin, were very diſcernable; and betwixt Sermons, Godly Conferences, &amp;c. very audible: whereat the Devil was ſo much enraged, that he forthwith ſtirred up his Inſtruments, the Epiſcopal-hireling-Preachers, who with Infernal bawlings, cried like the <hi>Jews</hi> of old, <hi>Men, Brethren, and Fathers, help, the whole Nation goeth after them.</hi> At which, their Ungodly <hi>Dioceſans</hi> were ſoon alarm'd, and by the Interceſſion of their wicked Privy Council, they procured a Tax to be laid upon the Nation for raiſing an Army to ſuppreſs thoſe Meetings, which they maliciouſly called <hi>Rendevouzes of Rebellion.</hi> And that the Inſtruments might be adapted to the Work, the Troops when raiſed, conſiſted of the Scum and Refuſe of the Nation: They bore the Characters of Wickedneſs on their Foreheads, and their Mouths were filled with Blaſphemy and Obſcenity. Their Officers would ſometimes curſe them, if they had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended any Women coming from Meetings, and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed them; yea, inſtances can be given, that they made the Houſes of the Epiſcopal Preachers, whoſe Cauſe they were rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to defend, their Stews, and their Wives and Daughters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came their Proſtitutes: and yet thoſe Miſcreants were ſo well pleaſed with thoſe Pillars of their Church, and Defenders of their Faith, that their ſullen Countenances were viſibly chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon their being Levied; and when they came to any Town, or Village, the Prelatiſts would inſult over the Presbyterians, and ask them, What they thought now?</p>
            <p>Thoſe Bloodhounds were at laſt imployed to ſearch out, fire upon, and diſperſe the Field-Meetings, which in many places they did, killed ſeveral upon the Spot, and filled the Jails of the Nation full; after which, the Council Baniſhed ſome, and ſold others for Slaves; ſome of which, were ſet at Liberty at the <hi>Thames</hi>-Mouth afterwards. The Landlords were made to give Bond, that thier Tenants ſhould not go to Meetings, and many times Fined upon that account. The Gentry were Fined, Confined, and Impriſoned, becauſe of their Ladies and Children going to Meetings. It was declared Treaſon, ſo much as to exchange a Word with many of the Meeters. At laſt, it came to that Criſis, That the People were forced to venture their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51902:7"/>Lives, and reſolve to defend themſelves and their Miniſters, or have no Ordinances at all; Whence happened divers Skirmiſhes, with various ſucceſs, but many times the Soldiers were baffled, and therefore they harraſſed the Country in the Night time, that no Perſon of any Morality could be quiet, but were diſturbed by their frequent, and rude Searches; in which they behaved themſelves with ſo much Barbarity, Blaſphemy, and Obſcenity, that they look'd liker <hi>Pagans,</hi> than Profeſſors of Chriſtianity; which confirmed the People in their diſſent, who readily argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That it could not be the Cauſe of Chriſt, which ſuch Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Hell were ſo zealous to maintain; nor, they his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who muſt imploy ſuch Miſcreants to procure them Hearers: And if at any time they apprehended ſuch as had been preſent at a Meeting, where Reſiſtance was made; or if they could but be proved, to have had a walking Sword at any Meeting, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there had been Reſiſtance or not; they were in hazard of their Lives, by their Ungodly Laws. <hi>James Learmont</hi> being Beheaded, for being at a Meeting where a Party of Soldiers were baffled, tho' it was proved, That he had nothing but a Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod in his hand. And the Laird of <hi>Knoll,</hi> a <hi>Teviotdale</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, narrowly eſcaped the like Fate, for being at a Meeting where there was no Reſiſtance, with a Sword about him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Neighbouring Gentleman, who was brought as a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt him, would ſwear no further, Than that he had a Staff, or a Scabbard under his Cloak, which the Jury could not find within reach of the Law. And by a continued Series of Tyrannical Proceedings, many of the moſt conſiderable, and ſubſtantial Yeomen, many conſiderable Citizens, ſome former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Magiſtrates of Corporations, and divers of the Gentry, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came liable to loſe their Lives by their wicked Laws: which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned their meeting together, ſometimes in pretty good po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of Defence to hear the Goſpel; and at ſuch a Meeting it was, where the Great Papa-Prelatical Champion <hi>Dundee,</hi> with a conſiderable Force of Foot and Dragoons, was routed by the Conduct of <hi>William Cleland,</hi> then a Boy; but afterwards, the immortaly famous Lieut. Colonel, who at <hi>Dunkel,</hi> with about Eight hundred Presbyterian Soldiers, routed the whole <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranno-Papa-Prelatical</hi> Hoſt, which conſiſted of near ſix thouſand Men; or if you will, Savage Beaſts in Human Shape. After the Defeat of <hi>Claverhouſe,</hi> at the ſaid Meeting, the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51902:8"/>concerned in the Reſiſtance, knowing they were deſtined to the Slaughter, if ever apprehended; and that the whole Country would be ruined for their ſakes, reſolved to keep toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their own Defence, to whom a great many others in like Circumſtances gathered in a little time, and if the Gentry had acted their parts as the People did theirs, or would but have vouchſafed them Conduct, in Probability <hi>Scotland</hi> had not at this Day been vexed with a graceleſs untoward Generation of Prelatiſis; from whom, as to the Differences betwixt us and them, we could never from firſt to laſt have any thing but Hectoring for Reaſon, Damning and Curſing for Argument: And <hi>it's the King's Will</hi> to ſatisfy our Objections from the Light of Nature, Word of God, and Conſcience enlightned by the ſame. Thus you have an Account of the Prelatical Hireling Curates, and of their Carriage before, and how the ſame oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned the Inſurrection at <hi>Bothwel</hi>-Bridg, and now follow ſome Inſtances of their Carriage after that was over.</p>
            <p>The D. of <hi>Monmouth</hi> having carried on that Affair with the Clemency and Generoſity natural to him, was maligned by our Prelatiſts, becauſe he did not ſacrifice the Priſoners to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge of thoſe Epiſcopal Furies, which they did themſelves af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in the moſt inhumane manner imaginable: for having ſent ſeveral Hundreds of them to Sea, the Ship was caſt away, (and that probably with Deſign) on the Coaſt of <hi>Orkney,</hi> and the ungodly Epiſcopal Brute the Captain, lock'd down the Hatches when the Ship was a ſinking, that they might be deſtroyed; ſo that none eſcaped but ſuch as were above Deck, which they were allowed to be in Parcels, leſt they ſhould have been ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered when altogether in the Hold; nor did the poor Remnant that were ſaved eſcape the bitter Taunts and Malice of the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copalians of that Place.</p>
            <p>And how intolerable the leaſt Favour ſhowed to the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians was to that reprobate Faction, is evident from the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Inſtances; When a great many of the Priſoners taken at the Inſurrection in 1666, formerly mentioned, were executed to ſatisfy the Fury of the ungodly Prelatiſts, the Court be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a little exorable, and ſent down a Pardon to the reſt, but that Limb of Antichriſt and infernal Locuſt, the Apoſtate Arch-Biſhop <hi>Sharp,</hi> being a Revolter, and conſequently profound
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51902:8"/>to make Slaughter, with a Malice like his Father the Devil, kept up the ſame till ſeveral more were executed; a Demon ſtration that the moſt implacable enraged Tyrant hath more Bowels of Mercy than a waſpiſh formal Prelate.</p>
            <p>In like manner when an Indulgence was granted to ſettle the, Minds of the People after the Inſurrection at <hi>Bothwel-Bridg</hi> the Generation of Vipers, the Epiſcopalian Seed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, did moſt bitterly revile the D. of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> whom they look'd upon as the Procurer of it, and flew in the Face of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty it ſelf, expreſſing themſelves in the Lady <hi>Hatton</hi>'s Dialect, <hi>What the Devil ſhall the K's Baſtard-Son govern us?</hi> And the unconſtant turn-coat Clergy, (ſome of whom while the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians kept in Arms, declared their Diſſatisfaction with Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and after their Defeat recanted again) by their Muſe <hi>Ninian Paterſon</hi> Curate of <hi>Liberton,</hi> publiſhed an obſcene ſcurrilous Lampoon, reflecting upon the Government for that Indulgence, which made ſome of the Epiſcopal Party themſelves wonder that ever ſuch a Fellow ſhould have been ſuffered to pollute a Pulpit afterwards: That you may taſte a little of their Poets Modeſty, I ſhall give you ſome of his Lines which occur to my Memory; In his <hi>Proaemium</hi> he addreſſes the King thus;
<q>
                  <l>We are like <hi>Jobs</hi> this <hi>19</hi> Years perplex'd,</l>
                  <l>Betwixt Deſtruction and Diſtraction vex'd;</l>
                  <l>And that, dread Sir, though not ſo ſtrange as true,</l>
                  <l>By Scabs and Devils, now indulg'd by you.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And Abundance more, a great deal worſe, which I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got. But that you may know that their Pen-men and Sword<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or if you will, Hectors and Buffoons, are near a-kin in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, you muſt underſtand this Clergy-Poet was famous and well known by the Name of <hi>Knaggs,</hi> a <hi>Scotch</hi> Word for a Pin to hang any thing one. The Occaſion of his being called ſo was thus: Coming on a time into a GEntlewoman's Chamber before ſhe was fully dreſſed, he took up her Neck-lace, which when ſhe enquired after, he told her he had hung it upon a Knag, and when ſhe asked where, he ſhewed it her hanging on his . . . . <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a very modeſt Epiſcopal Preacher.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51902:9"/>
            <p>Our Author ſays, the Epiſcopal Clergy generally complain'd of Violation of Juſtice under the late Adminiſtration; and though ſome were too acceſſary, others ſuffered for their Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and that the whole are not culpable for the Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of a few; which take it in the Complex, is a hateful Prevarication, and great Untruth: The Nation too well felt it, and ſmarts yet for it: That they generally in their Sermons, and otherwiſe, abetted the Tyranny of the Court, and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <hi>Anathema</hi>'s againſt thoſe that maintained the lawfulneſs of reſiſting Tyrants; and though, it's true, the honeſteſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them were turned out by the Teſt, that ſays nothing in defence of thoſe at preſent ejected. The Anti-Teſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thrown out in the Time of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently are too honeſt to have any ſhare in his Apology; and it's well known, the generality of thoſe who continued in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, went along with the Court in every thing, till ſuch time as Liberty was given to the Presbyterians (which was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways more intolerable to the Prelatiſts, than Liberty to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts) and then htey ſnuffed, not that they were angry with the Tyranny of the Manner, for it was according to their own Doctrine, that the King was emboldened to iſſue his Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſuch a tyrannical Stile; but that, like <hi>Cain,</hi> being conſcious to themſelves of their Brethrens Blood, they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to ſee them any way countenaced by thoſe in Power, (and for <hi>Cain</hi>'s Reaſon too) leſt every one that found them, ſhould kill them; for they knew well enough that the inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Laws, in their darling King <hi>James</hi>'s Time, which made it Death for any Nonconformiſts to preach, or People to hear them, were contrived by their Abettors, and paſſed by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Biſhops. They knew alſo that the brutiſh, impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, revengeful Tortures of <hi>Boots</hi> and <hi>Thumikins</hi> had been inflicted on the Presbyterians, by Advice of the Privy-Council, where their Biſhops were the moſt obdurate Spectators, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent ſpiteful movers of Queſtions to the poor tortured Priſoners. They knew further, that they had procured, and given conſent to the Antichriſtian-like Execution of Gentlemen within an hour after their Sentence, as <hi>Jerriſwood</hi> and others; like the practice of that Italian, who threatned to ſtab his Neighbour if he would not deny God; and when he had done
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51902:9"/>it, ſtabbed him notwithſtanding, that he might kill his Soul too, by allowing him no time to repent. They knew further, that their Prelats had ſat in Council, where Men were exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and threatned with Torture, to declare their Thoughts on ſuch an ſuch Points; and after having declared them, were hanged for the ſame, as <hi>James Skein</hi> and others; which was an invaſion on the Right of Mankind. Nay, Tyranny was come to ſuch an height, that their meaneſt ſcoundrel Officers would take upon them to examine as Judges, Perſons whom they had apprehended, and torture them with burnt Matches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt their Fingers, to tell the Miniſters Names who they had heard preach; and who of their Acquaintance were there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. And the baſe impudent Prieſts, whoſe Fathers were not good enough to eat with the Dogs of their Flocks, were hence incouraged to vomit out ſcurrilous Reflections upon their own Patrons Families, and thoſe of the greateſt Quality, becauſe favourers of Presbytery; they were ſo far from complaining of the Violation of Juſtice, as our lying Pamphleteer would inſinuate.</p>
            <p>In the next place, the Scribler mentions an Addreſs of the Scotiſh Biſhops, which he ſays very much incenſed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon inferior People againſt them, and pleads for ſome charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Allowance to that Action, becauſe of the Laws then in force; and ſeeing (as he ſays) they are willing to ſubmit to the Government, the Power of thoſe in Authority might be pleaſed to cover them from the Rage and Inſolence of the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>Wherein he ſhews himſelf plainly an Enemy to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. He paſſes over the Addreſs very ſmoothly, though it was that ſcandalous Libel againſt his preſent Majeſty when attempting our Deliverance: They who will, may read it in <hi>Gazette,</hi> Numb. 2398. <hi>Novemb.</hi> 12. 1688. and I ſhall only animadvert upon two or three Paſſages in it: And firſt, they reckon the long and <hi>illuſtrious Race of our Kings, the greateſt Glory of the Kingdom:</hi> Diametrically oppoſite to the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of all ſober Men, who (allowing that its due place) conſtantly affirm the greateſt Glory of that Nation to be their early and long profeſſion of the Chriſtian Religion, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51902:10"/>the firſt Fruits of the Gentiles, gifted unto Chriſt, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 2. amongſt the utmoſt Ends of the Earth; and in the Opinion of good Hiſtorians, bleſſed with the firſt Chriſtian King. But this Expreſſion of the Antichriſtian-Prelats, agrees very well with their Religion, <hi>an eſſential Part whereof,</hi> as they ſay themſelves, was, <hi>their ſtedfaſt Allegiance to the late King:</hi> which verifies from their own Mouths our Obſervation of them, that they and their Hirelings, inſtead of preaching Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners into Chriſt, have made it their Work to convert the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into a ſtupid ſlaviſh ſubjection to Tyranny, by them falſly called <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and their greateſt Argument, inſtead of <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> was, <hi>Thus ſaith the King:</hi> And indeed this is not to be wondered at, it being juſt with God to diſcover they were none of his Miniſters, but to fill them, as Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliders, with their own Ways, and make it evident they were the Miniſters of the King to whom they ſwore as Head of their Church, and had no other Miniſterial Power, but what they derived from him; and all who know them, muſt needs ſay they preached more againſt ſuch as oppoſed the Tyranny of their King, than againſt the moſt avowed Rebels to God and his Word: But their Brethren who poſſeſs the Pulpits now, are reſolved to avoid that Extream, and many of then chuſe rather to wreſt the Fifth Commandment to reach a Blow at their preſent Majeſties, than to inſiſt upon the Theme of Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to their King, though they bellowed it from the Pulpits, to procure ſubmiſſion to the hateful Tyranny of the two laſt Reigns: But their profound and univerſal ſilence on that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject now, and forbearing to declare their abhorrence of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Rebellion by the Prelatiſts, in conjunction with their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Papiſts, does ſufficiently demonſtrate what Friends they are to his preſent Majeſty, their Zeal for him bearing no proportion to their Zeal for the laſt two, they being eagerly forward then, to abhor Aſſociations, Petitions for Parliaments, and Inſurrections, yea, to degrade, as unworthy to be Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of their Church, Mr. <hi>Johnſon,</hi> &amp;c. who maintained the lawfulneſs of reſiſting Tyranny; but we ſee no ſuch publick Declarations againſt the Mutineers and Rebels now.</p>
            <p>But to return to the Prelates addreſs, they conclude with a preſumptuous Aſſurance, that God would give King <hi>James</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51902:10"/>the Necks of his Enemies, for which his preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty is very much obliged to them, who as they did then, they look upon him ſtill as his principal Enemy: but their Prayers, Faith and Undertakings were all of a Piece, and failed them moſt abominably; and they were thereby ſufficiently diſcovered to have no Intereſt with God, who rejected their preſumptuous Faith; nor with the People, for whoſe Aſſegiance they undertook, who did by their repreſentatives unanimouſly chuſe the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> their King, and at the ſame time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the Prelates as an inſupportable Grievance, and gave a Demonſtration to the World, that the Prelatical Maxim, <hi>No Biſhop, no King,</hi> is as falſe as the Devil the Author of it.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Scribler pleads for a charitable Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance to them, becauſe of the Laws then in Force: he forgot ſure that theſe very Laws were made by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of the Prelates and their Party, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently can be no Excuſe: And that the late K. was ſo well aſſured of their Adherence to him, that he expreſly commands the Viſcount <hi>Dundee</hi> to ſummon the Prelates and ſuch others as he confided in, to frame a Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of States in Oppoſition to the other: Neither has his Confidence failed him, for as they all owned him while they ſat in the Convention, their Party hath actually joined the Popiſh High-landers, <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> who fight for him ſince; and ſuch of them as were enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in our preſent King's Pay, betrayed his Forces twice to the Rebels: and this is all the Service he can ever expect from the <hi>Scots</hi> Prelatiſts.</p>
            <p>Next he tells you the ſaid Addreſs very much incenſed the Common People againſt them; as if his preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty had no other Friends there but ſuch, and that none of the Nobility and Gentry were incenſed at that raſcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Affront put on him by the Prelates: Sure he forgot that the Convention had not ſat long till it ſent the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats a going, and I hope they are not the common infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour ſort; and if his Majeſties great (but by them ill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved) Clemency had not prevented, it's not improbable
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51902:11"/>that thoſe Rabſhakeh and Shimei-like-Prelates had felt the Reſentments of others heavier than thoſe of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour ſort, for that ſcandalous Libel. And now I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but obſerve the Harmony betwixt the Papiſts and <hi>Scots</hi> Prelatiſts, the ſaying of this Pamphleteer agreeing ſo exactly with what the D. of <hi>Gordon</hi>'s Gentleman, late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come up, a violent known Papiſt, ſaid in a certain Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, That King <hi>William</hi> had none to own his Cauſe in <hi>Scotland</hi> but the inferiour Sort the Presbyterians: and tells a great many of the ſame impudent Lies concerning the ſevere Uſage of the Epiſcopal Clergy there, which are in this Pamphlet: whereby they deſign to render his Majeſties Government to the Church of <hi>England</hi> odious, that he ſhould ſuffer the <hi>Scots</hi> Epiſcopal-men to be ſo il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legally abuſed; which our Pamphleteer does alſo in a ſly manner inſinuate by ſaying,—The government might be pleaſed to protect them from the Inſolence of the Rabble, which is as much as to ſay (but a holliſh Lie) they do not.</p>
            <p>But granting them charitable Allowances for that Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, becauſe of the Laws then in Force: What can he ſay to juſtify their oppoſing his Majeſties Accoſſion to the Crown, when they were not under the dread of thoſe Laws, as it is known every Man of them did in the Convention, and that Arch Pimp of <hi>Glaſgow, Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> had the Impudence in their Face to maintain the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſs of depoſing the late King. Sure this ſays their Oppoſition was of Choice and not Fear; and tho they may be forced to ſubmit, yet how they can be dſteemed Loyal Subjects to a Government whoſe Being they oppoſed, I cannot underſtand.</p>
            <p>Our Author diſcovers no little Malice and Ignorance in his enumerating the ſorts of Presbyterians in Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineers, Cameronians, and Indulged: All <hi>Scots-men</hi> know the firſt two to be but one, and for his reckoning all the reſt Indulged, becauſe Accepters of the Liberty under King <hi>James,</hi> thinking thereby to bring an Odium upon them as Countenancers of the diſpenſing Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, nothing can be more malicious, as may be ſeen by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51902:11"/>their Addreſs, wherein they plainly tell him, their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples are contained in the Aſſemblies <hi>Confeſſion of Faith;</hi> which is far from owning any other Power in the Magiſtrate, than to encourage the Good, and puniſh the Wicked, and conſequently the Bounds of our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. This was not a cheating him with a pretended principle of Paſſive Obedience, and yet to dethrone him notwithſtanding, when he touched their Mitres; which gives us a new explanation of the Prelatical Maxim, <hi>No Biſhop, no King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another of his Reflections is, that they do not check nor reſtrain thoſe Cameronians, whom he charges with Anabaptiſtical Principles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which is a groſs Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, it being known, that ſeveral of thoſe Camero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians have been reclaimed by their Admonitions; and if the Malice of Hell did not induce the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiſts and Papiſts to obſtruct the ſettlement of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, there is no doubt of the reclaiming of the reſt, their difference not being ſo much in Principle, as in miſtaken Matters of Fact; and there are very few, if any of them, chargeable with thoſe <hi>German</hi> Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt Principles he talks of; though ſome, by the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of the late Government, abetted by the Prelatiſts, and for want of a free Exerciſe of Presbyterian Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline (which informs Mens Heads, but does not, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the Prelats, knock out their Brains) run into unwarrantable Exceſſes; and by miſtake con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, becauſe the late Government acted ſo like the Devil, that it was thereby diſſolved, and every one left to his Primitive Liberty; not conſidering, that the People had not then, though they have ſince, caſheer'd it by their Repreſentatives.</p>
            <p>And whereas he aggravates the turning out of ſome of the Prelatical Hirelings, before any thing was done in Parliament againſt them: There are none who throughly underſtand that Matter, will think it ſo culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as he would render it, eſpecially when it is conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that the Government was diſſolved, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in poſſeſſion of their Native Right, it will appear no
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51902:12"/>Wonder that they ſhould diſcharge ſuch to preach, as their Miniſters, who were obtruded upon them by Force, and into the Labours of Faithful Miniſters, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded by Violence; but eſpecially they being void of all Piety, having entred upon the Miniſtry with no other Deſign, but as Men do upon an ordinary Calling, to get a Livelihood, having no other Ordination, but the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of a prophane Biſhop, who arrogates to himſelf the ſole Power of Ordaining; and declares all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of the Reformed Churches abroad to be void, while he holds that of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be valid; and it being a known Practice amongſt them to chop and change Benefices for Advantages and Conveniency, as Men do Horſes and Cows. But whoſoever conſiders that theſe Hirelings had been the occaſion of ſo much Rapine, Profanity, Blod, and Devaſtation in the Weſt of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where, by their means, Sir <hi>Ja. Turner,</hi> with a Body of Helliſh, Prelatical, Lowland Souldiers, was brought to waſte the Country upon the account of Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity, as formerly hinted; and twice afterwards an Hoſt of Popiſh Savage Highlanders, (then the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Converters, and now their Champions) were brought upon them with a deſign to depopulate the Country in a time of great Peace and Quiet; by which means a Famine was brought on thoſe Parts, whereof many died, though the moſt induſtrious People in the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>If it be further conſidered, what they ſuffered af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards on the account of the Inſurrections at <hi>Both<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi>-Bridg, and that by the Earl of <hi>Argyle,</hi> both occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by the Prelatiſts, inſomuch that there was ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Family in the Weſt which had not ſuffered, either by Free-quarter, Fining, Confining, Rape, Exile, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Famine; yea, even many of the Prelatiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, either in their Families or Relations, it being very well known that the Highlanders ſpoiled all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtinction, where they could with conveniency; and were ſo brutiſh and inhumane, as to tear the Mort-cloaths, (or Pall,) from Corps going to be buried,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51902:12"/>which they afterwards converted into Caps. Now, I ſay, all theſe Barbarities conſidered, which that poor Country ſuffered upon the account of thoſe Hirelings, it may rather ſeem Matter of Wonder, that they ſhould have been ſo moderate as to content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with turning them out, and not have vented their Reſentments in the utter deſtruction of them, who had occaſioned the deſtruction of ſo many; and certainly if Grace had not ſubdued Humane Paſſion, they would have done ſo: And I appeal to the Prelatiſts own Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whether they could have carried it with ſo much moderation to thoſe who had but half ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured them.</p>
            <p>And as for the Contempt the People ſhewed of them, after the abolition of Epiſcopacy, it denotes how they had behaved themſelves when in Power; for, ſetting aſide ſome prophane Atheiſtical Wretches, it was never known that the generality of the People did ſo much vilify the Nonconformiſt Miniſters, when under the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt Laws: And it demonſtrates clearly, that they were under the Effects of the Threatning, <hi>becauſe they made the Sacrifice of the Lord Vile, he made them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible before the people;</hi> who if they had profited by them, would never have trampled upon them. And the true Reaſon of the Peoples diſregard, our Author by chance ingenuouſly acknowledges, though he did not intend ſo much, when he ſays in expreſs Terms, <hi>The Ejected complained not ſo much of their being depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as that all the Profits of the Year were denied them.</hi> It being juſt the vulgar and true obſervation of them, <hi>That they cared more for the Fleece, than for the Flock.</hi> And though as to Preaching ſucceſsfully and faithfully they were dumb Dogs, yet they could call for <hi>their Gain from their Quarter.</hi> And their complaining 2o much of their Danger from the People, puts me in mind of a Gentleman's Saying in the Weſt of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whoſe Protection they demanded, for fear of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, at their firſt being obtruded upon them; which was thus: <q rend="margQuotes">If you be God's Miniſters, let God protect
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51902:13"/>you; thoſe who were here before you, never needed nor ſought, our Protection: And it is a 2hrewd ground of ſuſpicion to the People, that you are not God's Miniſters, when you muſt have ſuch wicked Means and Inſtruments to preſerve you.</q> The poor man being conſcious of his own Wickedneſs, and knowing all their Abetters to be ſuch.</p>
            <p>Then he complains, that thoſe who would not pray as commanded, were ejected; wherein he hatefully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varicates, and deſignedly paſſes over what they were commanded to pray, <hi>viz.</hi> for <hi>their preſent Majeſties;</hi> which may be ſeen in the printed Journals of the Scotch Parliament; wherein all modeſt Men cannot but juſtify their Conduct; for though there might have been other Grounds enough to have deprived moſt of them, as Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, Inſufficiency, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet that they ſhould have no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to complain of prejudicated Judges, and that their Knavery might be evidenced to the World, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with a conſummate prudence, chuſed to make their Loyalty to the government their Teſt; and not one was authoritatively turned out, but upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of refuſing to pray for their Majeſties, and read the Declaration; and thoſe who were (deſervedly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough) turned out by the People, were by Act of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil reſtored again, till ſuch time as they underwent a legal Trial. But ſuppoſing it hard meaſure, if they had any Conſcience, they might herein acknowledg the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God, if they conſider that the Presbyterian Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters were turned out, meerly becauſe they would not acknowledg the Prelats, though willing enough to own the Civil Government: And Malice it ſelf muſt needs own the Moderation of our preſent Sovereign, when compared with their Darlings of Heaven, <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> that hanged thoſe, who upon better (though miſtaken) Principles, refuſed to pray for them. And if his preſent Majeſty exceed any way, it is in Mercy to thoſe who profeſſedly diſown his Title; for never was any Government known ſo mild towards thoſe who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to own it; and the leaſt Puniſhment that can be, is to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51902:13"/>turn ſuch from their Employments. And what kind of Friend to the Government this Pampheleteer is, who complains of Injuſtice in depriving of ſuch Men, may be caſily gueſſed.</p>
            <p>As for his hear-ſay Violences uſed to their Clergy, whereof the moſt atrocious Inſtances are the killing of one, and daubing his Face with Excrements, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing the Wife of another though in Child-bed; they are Helliſh Prelatical Lyes, and we challenge him to make good his Aſſertions, that any Presbyterians were concerned in thoſe Inhumanities, which if any ſuch hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, look liker the brutiſh impudent Fury of 2ome E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopalians, whoſe Relations have perhaps ſuffered by the Information or Rage of thoſe Curates, whoſe malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Carriage hath ſeveral times drawn upon them the Reſentments of thoſe of their own communion, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the Injuries offered to their Wives, Children, and remoter Relations, of which we can give many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances if needful: but that we may be aſſured they are impudent atrocious Lies, he neither gives Time, nor Place, nor Name of thoſe Perſons ſo abuſed, which to be ſure he would if he could: only he tells you, <hi>he has been told ſo, and he cannot certainly tell you who did it, though their Neighbours threatned thom:</hi> Juſt like the Inſtance of Papaprelatical Veracity uſed by the D. or <hi>York,</hi> and his Epiſcopal Council of <hi>Scotland</hi> againſt the Univerſity of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> when they had affronted him by burning the Pope in <hi>December</hi> 1680. they firſt alledged that the Students threatned to burn the Provoſt's Houſe, becauſe he like a Blockhead had ſuffered the King's Souldiers to enter the City (contrary to his own Oath, and the Towns Priviledges) to prevent the burning of the Pope, and when they had buzzed about this ſuppoſed Threatning, then they burn'd it themſelves, and charged the Students with it no make them odious, and find Occaſion of diſſolving the Univerſity, which they did for ſome time, and though the ſaid Students offered to come to any legal Trial for their Vindication, it was never accepted, becauſe the Council knew it could be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51902:14"/>proved that ſome of the Duke's Livery were ſeen come from the Houſe, juſt as it took fire, and that a Barrel of Powder having the Caſtle-Mark on it, which it was not poſſible for any to come at, but from the King's Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, was found in the Park near the ſaid Houſe: The moſt violent Proſecutors of the ſaid Students, were the Biſhops of St. <hi>Andrews, Edinburgh,</hi> and the profane Ruſſian Sir <hi>William Ratherſon,</hi> then Clerk to the council, and as great a Whore-maſter as his Brother the Biſhop, who both of them particularly, when the Students were examined by the Council about the Pope-burning, took care to have that Queſtion ask'd at them, if they went to Church, knowing the Prelatiſts had not ſuch a Hatred at Popery as the others; which as it was diſcovered then, appears above board now, when they joyn actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the Papiſts in Arms againſt the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in that Kingdom, and according to our laſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices from <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Robels build their great Hopes upon an Aſſociation of the <hi>Scots</hi> Prelatiſts, who have ſworn Allegiance to their preſent Majeſties, that they may have the greater Opportunity of undermining them.</p>
            <p>Our Author in the next place reſolves to give us a touch of his Hyperbolical (or rather helliſh becauſe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) Oratory, <hi>That it's beyond the Power of Words to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their Miſery to that Degree as they ſuffer it.</hi> But I would have him to remember that there are Epiſcopal Inhumanities which we have felt of a far higher Nature than thoſe he falſly alledges they ſuffer, <hi>viz.</hi> Rapes, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, Murder, Hanging, Drowning, Beheading, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, torturing with Boots, Thumikins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which we have Words to expreſs, and pray if he can let him give us Inſtances of their Sufferings to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</p>
            <p>This next Reflection is upon the want of Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in many Churches for ſome Months: to which he may readily be anſwered, That moſt of them have wanted it ever ſince the Reſtitution of Prelacy, for what Service has been in them ſince, it has by its Effects
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51902:14"/>proved far enough from being Divine, as may be ſeen by their want of Converts, of which we challenge the whole Party to produce any if they can; Perverts we are ſure they may: and therefore we give them the like Choice, as <hi>Elijah</hi> gave to <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prieſts; <hi>The God that anſwereth by Fire, let him be God.</hi> Let thoſe whoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry God has owned by the Seal of Converſion, be his Miniſters, and the others not; and we are ſure to find the <hi>Scots</hi> Prelatical Curates to be excluded, and that Threatning exactly fulfilled on them, <hi>Becauſe you ran, and I have not ſent you; therefore you ſhall not profit my People:</hi> whereby God hath owned our Cauſe, and maintained the Truth of our Arguments againſt their Miſſion and Ordination. Not that I would accuſe all who cannot perhaps give Proof of their Miniſtry by Converſion as no Miniſters, knowing that God is So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, and may uſe in that Work whom he pleaſes, but I ſay that conſidering their way of Ordination, and coming in upon Flocks which they have maintained af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo much Light to the contrary, in Oppoſition to that Way which is clearly exhibited in the Word, their Univerſal want of Succeſs, while God hath bleſſed their Oppoſites with it, is to me as viſible a Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration that God owns our Cauſe, and diſowns theirs, as his burning up of <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Sacrifice, while that of the <hi>Baalicolites</hi> remained untouched, was, that he owned him as his Prophet, and diſowned them.</p>
            <p>And that ſome Churches are unprovided, and others not ſo well as they ſhould be, is no Reflection upon us, but on themſelves, who have by their Inhumanity dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the Number of our Miniſters, prevented the breeding up of others, and at preſent obſtruct the Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of our Church, by their horrid Lies, and ſly malicious Inſinuations. But when their Party was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant, I have ſeen ſeveral Churches, nay I am ſure the moſt part of the Churches in ſome Counties, where there was little or no Divine Service, as they call it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the People could not be prevail'd upon to come and hear them, and in that caſe let any Man judg whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51902:15"/>it be fit to impoſe ſuch a Miniſter whom the People would not hear? or where have they a Precedent in the Scripture for ſuch Practices?</p>
            <p>Next he tell us that the Nobility, Gentry, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort of the Commonalty reſpect the Perſons and Functions, and extreamly commiſerate the Condition of their Clergy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—A Maſs of malicious Impudence! Was it not the Nobility and Gentry, and the Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the Commonalty, that made thoſe Laws which turn'd them out, and decalred the Function of their Biſhops an inſupportable Grievance to the Nation? Where were their Advocates then, why did they not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in Parliament, or wherefore did not their Nobility and Gentry, if there were ſo many of them, enter their Proteſtation againſt thoſe Laws? We hear but of very few of their Advocates there, and thoſe who did plead for them, were ſuch as had been imbrued in Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Blood, and conſequently under <hi>Cain</hi>'s Dread, and have been actually queſtioned ſince by the Parliament, as diſſaffected to the preſent Government: and the Truth is, they have few Friends but ſuch as if they had Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er would moleſt it, as the late Viſcount <hi>Dundee,</hi> who was the firſt that made any Appearance for them, and did at the ſame time declare againſt the Government: And that the better ſort of the Commonalty are their Friends, is a helliſh Lie, except the Ignorant, Proſane, Swearing, Curſing, Drunken, Whoring Rabble, and ſuch as have no Worſhip of God in their Families (as not one in a thouſand of the Prelatiſts have ſo much as the Form of it) be the beſt, and thoſe who walk in the contrary steps be the worſt: I appeal to their own Conſciences if they do not know this to be true, and to all Men of any Morality, who make Conſcience of ſpeaking Truth to ſay to the contrary if they can, and whether this Aſſertion of his be not an impudent Lie in the Face of God and Man, it being very well known that debauched Perſons were always their greateſt Friends, and that the Generality of thoſe who had any Piety were their profeſſed Oppoſers.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:51902:15"/>
            <p>And as for their Clergy's Inclinations to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy, and comforting their Souls with it in their Diſtreſs. Whatever Influence it may have upon many of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy to aſſiſt them, who will a thouſand to one be readier to do that, than ſwear Allegiance to their Soveraigns, it will be found but an inauſpicious Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with their own Country-men, and perhaps may arm the Good-women with their Folding-ſtools once more againſt them, as it did formerly in <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt's time, when one of the Biſhops begun to read the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer (which ſhe called <hi>Papery</hi>) in her Ears. And indeed it verifies what the Diſſenters have always ſaid of them, that they were ſtrangers to the Power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and not knowing how to pray without, muſt now have Recourſe to a Form, of which whatever need may be pretended for the Weak, they are as unreaſonable and unnatural an Impoſition upon the Strong, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally on Miniſters in the Exerciſe of all their Miniſterial Duties, as would be the impoſing of Crutches upon the Adult and able part of Mankind, who can walk better without them; and uſe them who will, if they have any Experience of Chriſtianity on their Souls, they will quickly find the beſt of their Forms as defective and ill ſuited to their various Needs, as the poor Man did, who came to the Parſon for a Prayer to quench his burning Houſe.—The Prieſt turning over his Book, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none for the purpoſe, at laſt bethought himſelf of that for Rain, which being only for moderate Showers; the poor Man finding that not to reach his caſe, cried, <hi>Nay, Good Lord, whole Buckets full, for moderate Showers will not do my turn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His topping Reflection comes next, that the <hi>Scots</hi> Presbyterians pray <hi>that God will put down the Anti-Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Hierarchy</hi> alſo in <hi>England.</hi> But he ſuppoſes that to proceed from Zeal, rather than Encouragement of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, though he wiſhes there were no Features in the preſent Face of things that encourages ſuch ſad Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtications;—<hi>Hinc illae lacrymae.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:51902:16"/>
            <p>Pray good Sir, Is it not as lawful for the <hi>Scots</hi> Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians to pray againſt the Hierarchy as <hi>Anti-chriſtian,</hi> as it was for a Metropolitan of <hi>England</hi> in the laſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to declare the <hi>Diſſenters were not Chriſtians?</hi> and be it known to his Lordſhip, I'le undertake to prove the former, as ſoon as he ſhall have made good the latter. Or, farther, why may not the <hi>Scots</hi> Presbyterians as well pray againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hierarchy, as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and Prelates too, Plot, Drink, and Plead (we know where) againſt the <hi>Scots</hi> Presbytery? and I believe they would pray againſt it alſo, but that they have not a Form for it, whih they may eaſily provide for now, that they are about mending the Liturgy, and then there will be <hi>quid pro quo</hi>—. And whereas he ſuppoſes they are not herein encouraged by Authority: If he means the Authority of <hi>England,</hi> it's Nonſenſe, for they have nothing to do with it: but if he mean the Authority of <hi>Scotland,</hi> he diſcovers his Ignorance and Saucineſs; for it is plain they have done what was proper for a Civil Government (as ſuch) to do, <hi>viz.</hi> they have declared the Hierarchy (as to their own part) <hi>Antihumane,</hi> that is, contrary to the Peoples Inclinations, and an inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Grievance to the Nation; and I ſuppoſe are ſo good natured to wiſh their Neighbours were rid of it too; and ſo much the rather that they have ſo often found, and do ſtill find their impoſing ſawcy Intrigues againſt the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where they have nothing to do; wherein if they perſiſt, it may perhaps (and let them blame themſelves for it) prove as fatal to them as it did in the Days of <hi>Laud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſeeing our Author is ſo good a Phyſiognomiſt, as to diſcover Features in the preſent Face of Affairs, encouraging ſuch ſad Prognoſtications as the Fall of the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Hierarchy, he would have done well to have diſcovered them, that if poſſible the Effects might be prevented; but this I ſuppoſe is reſerved to the next <hi>Seſſion at the Devil,</hi> where the Pillars of the Hierarchy, it's poſſible, may find ſome new Props, or Buttereſſes, if his Majeſty's Oath, repeated Aſſurances,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51902:16"/>and Acts of Parliament, be not Security enough. But though the Scribler would by this Inſtance, according to the uſual practices of the Papiſts, (whereof the Church of <hi>England</hi> will never learn to be aware) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe them againſt his Majeſty, as endeavouring to bring in Presbytery, becauſe he has in ſome part gratified the Inclinations of his Majeſty's Subjects in <hi>Scotland:</hi> they may aſſure themſelves, that ſo long as they can ſecure to their Hierarchy the Inclinations of the generality of the People of <hi>England,</hi> they need not fear that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, who aboliſhed it, to ſatisfy the Inclinations of his People in <hi>Scotland,</hi> will do the like here, contrary to the Inclinations of his People in <hi>England;</hi> having drawn his firſt Breath in a Country where the People are ſuffered to follow their Inclinations in Matters of Religion, and not cudgell'd (according to the manner of ſome) into a Ceremonial Uniformity, where there is a ſubſtantial Multiformity. And there would be ſo much the leſs hazard of their loſing the Inclinations of the People, if the People perceived his Majeſty had more of theirs; for they cannot ſuppoſe the People ignorant, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all of the Hierarchy (Biſhops at leaſt) oppoſed his coming to the Crown of <hi>England;</hi> which in a great meaſure obſtructed the Relief, and conſequently occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned the Ruin of <hi>Ireland;</hi> nor that they do not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how the Metropolitan of all <hi>England,</hi> and too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the reſt, diſown him ſtill: Nor have they forgot, that upon the Oppoſition the Abdication and Vacancy of the Throne met with from the Mitred Lords; that when the Matter came to the Lower Houſe again, they were followed by about 150 of the Commons; and conſequently the Nation at the very brink of Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by the moroſity of the Mitres, which occaſioned ſevere Reflections upon them by ſome of their own Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronets, <hi>viz.</hi> That they generally found the Biſhops to be againſt that which was for the Nation's Good, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And howſoever the late Oppoſition which they made to the late King may be magnified; they ſeem quickly to have repented of it, when ſo many of the ſame Men
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51902:17"/>are at this Day oppoſite to his preſent Majeſty's Title. But ſuppoſing they had continued ſtedfaſt to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion's Intereſt; whatever good Nature might have done, I am ſure Juſtice would not have awarded them any Thanks, but ſuch as are due to Him, who after he hath broke my Head, allows me a Plaiſter: Which will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear undeniably true, if we conſider that they threw out the Bill of Excluſion, which makes them chargeable with all the Miſchiefs paſt, preſent, and to come, from that unhappy Reign. And if they perſiſt in ſuch Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, it cannot but be thought that, early or late, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may come to enquire what ſort of Men they were who preached up Diſpenſing Power, Paſſive Obedience, Non-reſiſtance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And who were the moſt zealous in promoting Abhorrences of Petitions for a Parliament, reading <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Declaration for diſſolving that of <hi>Oxford,</hi> promiſing to aſſiſt and ſtand by him and the Duke of <hi>York;</hi> publiſhing the Proteſtant Plots from their Pulpits; whence they ridiculed that of the Papiſts; which the Mitres are ſtill ſo unwilling to have believed, that moſt of them oppoſed the reverſing of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Perjury</hi> given againſt Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> who (though little regarded) did the Nation more Service than the Seven idolized Stars, ſo many of whom are now turned dark Lanthorns. Nor can it ever be forgot how many of the Inferior Clergy, following the conduct of their Triple-headed Guide, advanced the Intereſt of the Triple Crown, and ſome of them topping Ones too, at the Hour of Death, grated with their ſlaviſh Non-ſenſical Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance, upon the Conſciences of the Noble Hero's and Darlings of the People, the Lord <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> upon the very Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folds: and if the contrary Doctrine be damnable, as they alledged then, I am ſure their Church hath been guilty of damnable Practices ſince.</p>
            <p>As for his malicious Inſinuation, That it is not the want of Affection to the preſent Eſtabliſhment that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſes the People of <hi>Scotland</hi> againſt the Epiſcopal Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he may remember that he contradicts himſelf in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51902:17"/>firſt Page, where he ſays, That the Addreſs of the Biſhops againſt the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> incenſed the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or People againſt them: So we ſee the Proverb verified, that <hi>Liars had need of good Memories.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas he ſays, That ſome of the Clergy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled <hi>Scotland,</hi> conform in all Points when they came to <hi>England,</hi> it needs better proof than his Aſſertion to give it credit: For what Reaſon can there be to own his Majeſty's Authority in <hi>England,</hi> that might not have prevailed with them to do it in <hi>Scotland?</hi> Let any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Anſwer be given to this; and if there be any who do that here, pretending they were turned out by Authority upon anyother Account there, or that they may not have the Protection of Authority to ſtay there; he would do well to give us their Names, and we doubt not to prove them Infamous, Scandalous, Lying Runna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, of which we know there are too many who make it their Work to incenſe the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt, and make them jealous of his Majeſty: Of which Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this Pamphleteer ſeems to be, by his malicious Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation, <hi>That Ceſar's Ear is not open to hear their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints;</hi> a ſeditious Reflection, as if his Majeſty denied Common Juſtice to any of his Subjects; which Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is obliged to enquire into and puniſh.</p>
            <p>And whereas he alledges, That the Sufferings of theſe infamous Hirelings, are not unlike thoſe of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians. To which of the Saints will he turn him? or where will he find an Inſtance in the Primitive Church, That the Miniſters adhered to a perſecuting Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Prince, brought to the Crown by Force and Fraud, againſt a Chriſtian King duly elected by the People? Let him give me ſuch an one, <hi>Et erit mihi Magnus Apollo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to conclude, with a true Character of theſe Scotiſh Prelatiſts, They are not ſuch as out of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence decline to own the preſent Government; but knowing themſelves either to have been wicked Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, of ſcandalous Lives, or Inſufficient, ſo as that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51902:18"/>they could not be continued in the Paſtoral Charge un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any good Government; They thought it beſt to come off with a little Credit, and pretend Loyalty to the Abdicated Prince.</p>
            <p>I conclude, with an obteſtation to all ſober Men, not to regard the Gain-ſayings of Hectors, Ruffians, prophane Fellows, Curſers <hi>Jacobites,</hi> Swearers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to any thing here delivered, though they ſhould confirm their Atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations with execrable Oaths, for they may be ſure that ſuch as make no Conſcience to ſwear, will make none to lie.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
